All right, we start with so on today's דף daf is דף
כ. Daf Kaf. Before we start, of course, I just want to
say that together with all of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, we mourn
the passing of the three Israeli teens, יעקב נפתלי בן רחל דבורה,
Yaakov Naftali ben Rachel Devorah, גלעד מיכאל בן בת גלים, Gilad Michael
ben Bat Galim, and אייל בן איריס תשורה. Eyal ben Iris Teshurah.
You know, we as with all of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael have
been praying for them over these last few weeks. And as we
learned in מסכת תענית, Masechet Taanit, sometimes the prayers are not answered,
and there comes a point where sometimes the period of praying has
to transition into a period of mourning and accepting the loss, accepting
the tragedy. So we all,
it's going to be, last night there was of course a gathering,
prayer vigil, memorial
vigil in midtown, and we just will continue to find opportunities together
with כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael to mourn their passing and to wish
נחמה nechama for their families and for all of Israel. At the
end of our דף, daf, we'll say a אל מלא Kel Maleh
in their memory.
So we resume now on י"ט עמוד ב Yud Tet Amud Bet
with תניא. Tania. אמר רבי אליעזר בן פרטא, Amar Rabbi Eliezer ben
Prata, מיום שחרב בית המקדש. miyom shecharav Beit Hamikdash. The line starts
with the word המקדש, Hamikdash, it's about twenty lines down in the
wide lines. מיום שחרב בית המקדש, Miyom shecharav Beit Hamikdash, נעשו גשמים
צימוקים. na'asu geshamim tzimukim. From the time that the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash was destroyed, rains have become raisins. No, the rains have become
shriveled up. We don't have the rains the way they used to
be when there was a בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. לעולם צימוקים לעולם.
Le'olam tzimukim le'olam. יש שנה שגשמיה מרובין, Yesh shanah shegeshameiha merubin, ויש
שנה שגשמיה מועטין. veyesh shanah shegeshameiha muatin.
So it's always, you know, less than it used to be. True,
there are years in which the rains are many, plentiful; years in
which the rains are scarce. יש שנה שגשמיה יורדין בזמנן. Yesh shanah
shegeshameiha yordin bizmanan. There's times which, as we learned earlier throughout it's
about how much rain, it's about the timing of the rain, there're
times in which the years' rain is in the right time. ויש
שנה שאין גשמיה יורדין בזמנן. Veyesh shanah she'ein geshameiha yordin bizmanan.
Times when it doesn't come in the right time. שנה שגשמיה יורדין
בזמנן למה הוא דומה? Shanah shegeshameiha yordin bizmanan l'mah hu domeh? When
it comes in the right times, what's that year like? לעבד שנתן
לו רבו פרנסתו באחד בשבת, L'eved shenatan lo rabbo parnasato be'echad beshabbat,
a slave that the master gave him his, you know, his sustenance,
the flour that he'll need to or, you know, the raw materials
he'll need of the food that he'll need for the week on
Sunday. נמצאת עיסה נאפת כתיקנה ונאכלת כתיקנה. Nimtzeit issah ne'efet kitiknah vene'echelet
kitiknah.
So the bread is baked in its right time and it's eaten
its right time. You know, you have you have all the stuff
and you can prepare and you can do things and give things
the time that they need. שנה שאין גשמיה יורדין בזמנן. Shanah she'ein
geshameiha yordin bizmanan.
When the rains do not come in the right time. למה הוא
דומה? L'mah hu domeh? What is it similar to? לעבד שנתן לו
רבו פרנסתו בערב שבת. L'eved shenatan lo rabbo parnasato be'erev shabbat. That
you have your food, you're given all your food at the last
minute on ערב שבת. erev shabbat. נמצאת עיסה נאפת שלא כתיקנה. Nimtzeit
issah ne'efet shelo kitiknah.
The bread is not baked in the right time. It doesn't you
don't have the time to do it properly. ונאכלת שלא כתיקנה Vene'echelet
shelo kitiknah and it's eaten not in the right time. Again, it's
a little bit funny what the need is for the משל. mashal.
You would think that people would understand, you know, sort of transparently
what the problem is when the rains don't come in the right
time. But the probably the power is not in making you understand
the, you know, the
practical implications of not having rain in the right time and how
it will affect the crops, but it's again to re-surface that image
of the עבד eved and the רב, rav, which in a way
goes back to the very first משנה, mishnah, right, which is when
it rains on סוכות, Sukkot, it's a סימן קללה. siman kelalah. And
the סימן קללה siman kelalah of it raining on סוכות Sukkot is
that famous משנה mishnah in סוכות, Sukkot, which is when it rains,
it's like what? It's like the servant comes to serve water to
the master and the master right spills it on the servant. So
again, the whole idea of rain is God communicating with us and
is evoking this relationship where the where the children where the servant's
God is the master. What do we read into this? So presumably
again the purpose of this metaphor is not like, oh look, things
will be difficult if it rains at the wrong time. But no,
thinking about this in terms of our relationship and our dynamics with
God, to me seems to be the point of making this metaphor.
Okay, and then it goes on and
says שנה שגשמיה מרובין. shanah shegeshameiha merubin. If
there's a lot of rain. מהו דומה? Mahu domeh? What's it similar
to? לעבד שנתן לו רבו פרנסתו בבת אחת. L'eved shenatan lo rabbo
parnasato bevat achat. So the master got his gave gave the servant
his his sustenance all at one time.
So meaning not just day by day, presumably, although it's a little
bit funny because we just spoke about getting it on Sunday presumably
for the week. So רש"י Rashi here says it means you got
the whole years all at one time. So you have you know
you got you got a lot of stuff. So it's not just
enough time to plan, for that you need a week. So what's
the implications? having all of this well in advance? So נמצאת ריחיים
טוחנת מן הכור מה שטוחנת מן הקב nimtzet reicha-im tochenet min hakur
mah shetochenet min hakav נמצאת עיסה אוכלת מן הכור כמו אוכלת מן
הקב. nimtzet isa ochelet min hakur k'mo ochelet min hakav. So what
you get
is you get the economy of scale that now when you are
going to grind it in the millstone, the amount of waste that
comes out of a כור kur which is a huge amount, right,
is only equivalent to the enormous amount of waste that comes when
you do a קב kav which is a small amount. Okay? So
the amount of waste is going to be the same presumably, I
don't know why it's proportional, but presumably there is
this economy of scale. So if you're doing a lot at a
time, then it's the same amount
of
food that goes to waste, but it's a tiny, it's a very
tiny percentage. And similarly, that when you make the flour into dough,
the amount that gets wasted from a whole כור's kur worth of
dough is equivalent only to the tiny amount that gets wasted when
it's a קב. kav. So the same objective amount is going to
be wasted, but when you do a larger scale, obviously then the
implications are much more efficiency. A little bit more beneficial.
What?
Not just a bit beneficial.
When it's a lot of rain. Is it late? No, no, no.
First we did the comparison early versus late, and now we're doing
the comparison a lot versus a little. Right, so there's the two
things, okay? So early versus late is you have enough time and
you do things in enough time, others you're rushed. A lot is
you have the economy of scale. Again, which is like bizarre, isn't
a lot just better? I mean in terms of too much, what's
the whole point of the metaphor? But maybe the idea is that
there are hidden benefits of the a lot of rain that you
otherwise maybe wouldn't have appreciated.
Is it a lot or is it concentration?
Well, so that's true, that's the problem with the metaphor, meaning that
the case is a שנה שגשמיה מרובים shanah shegeshameha merubim as opposed
to a שנה שגשמיה מועטין shanah shegeshameha muatin which basically is not
concentration, it's just absolute quantity, but the metaphor is are you getting
it like the whole year's worth at once or spread over time.
So that's what I said, I don't exactly get why the metaphor
is necessary and like it doesn't even exactly parallel. But again, maybe
the only point is sometimes there are these economies of scale, these
other hidden benefits you don't realize.
There's
another Rashi. What? There's another Rashi that says when a large amount
falls at one time, more water reaches the productive
soil than when the amount of rain is spread.
Right, so that explains the economy of scale, there's always going to
be a certain amount that's absorbed into the ground before it becomes
productive, so if you get a lot, then the amount that needs
to get absorbed is a tiny proportional to the amount that actually
pierces through and is able to be as helpful. So thank you,
that's helpful. So there is the similar type of economy, there's a
similar type of a benefit that the amount that goes to waste
is proportionally a smaller amount in that case. Okay, דבר אחר. davar
acher. Okay where are we? נמצאת עיסה. nimtzet isa. Okay, בזמן שגשמיה
מרובים. bizman shegeshameha merubim. בזמן שגשמיה מועטין למה הוא דומה לעבד שנתן
לו רבו
פרנסתו מעט מעט. bizman shegeshameha muatin l'mah hu domeh l'eved shenatan lo
rabbo parnasato me-at me-at.
You only get it bit by bit. Okay, and again here the
comparison is not exact because this seems to be the same amount
but spread over time. נמצאת ריחיים מה שטוחנת מן הכור טוחנת מן
הקב נמצאת עיסה כמה שנאכלת מן הכור אוכלת מן הקב. nimtzet reicha-im
mah shetochenet min hakur tochenet min hakav nimtzet isa kamah shena-chelet min
hakur ochelet min hakav. So now it's the opposite, just the same,
I mean it's the exact same point but it's like, oh, the
same amount of waste that would come from a huge amount is
now coming from a small amount and the same amount of waste
in making the dough that would come from a huge amount is
now coming from a small amount, which means the amount of waste
is always an absolute amount but now the proportions are much more
against you because you do not have the economy of scale. And
somehow as it was pointed out right, רש"י Rashi says that when
it rains a lot, there's a certain amount that's not going to
be beneficial and therefore it is a much smaller proportion when there
is a lot of rain. Okay, דבר אחר בזמן שגשמיה מרובים למה
הוא דומה לאדם שמגבל את הטיט. davar acher bizman shegeshameha merubim l'mah
hu domeh l'adam shemegabel et hatit. A person that is like making
plaster. אם יש לו מים רבים im yes lo mayim rabim
if there's a lot of water to add to the mix as
he's making the plaster so מים אינם כלים והטיט מגובל יפה, mayim
einam kalim vehantit megubal yafeh, the water doesn't run out and the
plaster gets made very well. אם יש לו מים מועטין im yesh
lo mayim muatin if he only has a very scarce amount of
water, מים כלים והטיט אינו מתגבל, mayim kalim vehantit eino mitgabel, then
you run out of the water and the plaster does not get
made well. Again, very funny, what is the need exactly to give
this metaphor and I can't even say what I said before about
the עבד eved and the רב rav because here there's no עבד
eved and רב. rav. So anyway, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Okay, new
ברייתא. braita. פעם אחת עלו כל ישראל לרגל לירושלים. pa-am achat alu
kol yisrael laregel l'yerushalayim.
One day, one time all of the Jewish people came on the
רגל regel to Jerusalem ולא היה להם מים לשתות. velo haya lahem
mayim lishtot. Almost sounds like it's quoting last week's
פרשה parsha right ולא היה מים לעדה
ולא היה מים לשתות. velo haya mayim la-edah velo haya mayim lishtot.
Jewish or not Jewish. אמר לו amar lo *Amar lo*, he said
to me, we'll see later in the story if it becomes any
clearer. אמר לו amar lo *Amar lo*, הלווני שתים עשרה מעיינות מים
shteim esre ma’ayanot mayim, לעולי רגלים *Halveini shteim esrei ma'ayanot mayim le'olei
regalim*, lend me 12 springs of water, 12 wells of water for
those that are coming up for the רגלים *regalim*. Exactly how do
you lend the wells? Let us use the wells! Okay. ואני אתן
לך שתים עשרה עינות מים *Ve'ani eten lecha shteim esrei einot mayim*,
and I will pay you back, and also not exactly clear, does
it mean I'll pay you back all the water that they drank,
I'll give you back what I took, then it's no benefit, then
why would I lend it to you? But okay, maybe I'll give
you, I'll give you other ones in addition to these ones. Let's
say for now it means I'll give you back the water that
they drank. ואם איני נותן לך *Ve'im eini noten lecha*, and if
I don't pay you back the water that they drank, ואם איני
נותן לך שתים עשרה כיכר כסף *ve'im eini noten lecha shteim esrei
kikar kasef*, הריני נותן לך שתים עשרה כיכר כסף *hareini noten lecha
shteim esrei kikar kasef*. I will give you 12 talents of silver,
an enormous amount of money, huge amount of money. Yeah, yeah, yeah,
huge amount of money. It sounds also a little bit like a,
what do you call it, Merchant of Venice, right? If I don't,
no? Okay, people don't see the comparison? What?
Just a classic pound
of flesh, I do understand that it's like a huge consequence. Well,
we'll see what will happen, okay? Huge consequence if you don't make
it by the right time. Or maybe that was a weird comparison.
וקבע לו זמן *Vekava lo zman*, and he set it as a
time. כיון שהגיע הזמן ולא ירדו גשמים *Keivan shehiggia hazman velo yardu
geshamim*, so the time came and it had not yet rained. Okay,
it was time to pay back. He had thought that by this
time it would already rain and he would give them back the
wells and they would be, it would have rained, they would have
refilled with water. Now he's giving them back the wells and they're
still mostly empty. Of course, the רש"י *Rashi* makes the question that
don't the if they're מעיינות ma’ayanot *ma'ayanot* don't they refill from underground,
from underground sources? Not exactly clear. Maybe cisterns. Could be, but he
says מעיינות ma'ayanot, *ma'ayanot*. Anyway, okay, ולא ירדו גשמים *velo yardu geshamim*.
בשחרית שלח לו *Beshacharit shalach lo*, so
in the morning he sent him, שגר לי או מים או מעות
*shagar li o mayim o ma'ot*, send me either the water or
the money you owe me, שיש לי בידך *sheyesh li beyadecha*, that
I have in your hand, meaning that you owe me. שלח לו
*Shalach lo*, עדיין יש לי זמן כל היום כולו *Adayin yesh li
zman kol hayom kulo*, wait, wait, wait, there's still time. כל היום
כולו שלי *Kol hayom kulo sheli*, I've got the rest of the
day. בצהרים שלח לו *Betzaharaim shalach lo*, in the afternoon he sent
him, שגר לי או מים או מעות *shagar li o mayim o
ma'ot*, send me either the water or the money, שיש לי בידך
*sheyesh li beyadecha*. שלח לו *Shalach lo*, עדיין יש לי שהות ביום
*adayin yesh li shahut bayom*, hey, I still have time in the
day. במנחה שלח לו *Bemincha shalach lo*, in the afternoon he sent
him, שגר לי או מים או מעות *shagar li o mayim o
ma'ot*, give me water or money, שיש לי בידך *sheyesh li beyadecha*.
שלח לו *Shalach lo*, עדיין יש לי שהות ביום *adayin yesh li
shahut bayom*, it's only מנחה *mincha* time, I still have time in
the day. ליגלג עליו אותו אדון adon *Ligleg alav oto adon*, so
that wealthy person mocked him. אמר Amar, כל השנה כולה לא ירדו
גשמים *Amar kol hashana kula lo yardu geshamim*, you had a year,
so that's interesting, he had a year to pay back, or no,
maybe he didn't have a year to pay it back, but it
hasn't rained for a year. As was pointed out, it doesn't any
naturally rain over the summer, here everybody is coming up in סוכות
Sukkot *Succos* time, we just had situations in which it doesn't rain
in סוכות *Succos* time and you're already at פסח Pesach *Pesach* time
in, you know, that was the story of חוני המעגל Choni Hama'agel
*Choni Hama'agel* that it was פסח *Pesach* time, so it's been about
a year since the last rain. So for a whole year it
hasn't rained, ועכשיו ירדו גשמים *ve'achshav yardu geshamim*? Now you think on
this very last minute of the last day that you have to
pay me back it's going to rain? נכנס לבית המרחץ בשמחה *Nichnas
leveit hamerchatz besimcha*, he went into the bathhouse in joy, and of
course as the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* points out, he was even further
mocking him, he's there going to use the water to just bathe
himself when everybody else needs water presumably for even more basic human
needs. עד שאדון נכנס בשמחתו לבית המרחץ *Ad she'adon nichnas besimchato leveit
hamerchatz*, while the wealthy person was going in in joy into his
into the bathhouse, נקדימון Nakdimon נכנס לבית המקדש *Nakdimon nichnas leBeit Hamikdash*.
Nakdimon went into the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. *Beit Hamikdash* כשהוא עצב
*keshehu atzev*, when he was in sad in anguish. נתעטף ועמד בתפילה
nitattef ve’amad bitfillah, *Nit'atef ve'amad bitfila*, he wrapped himself presumably in his
טלית *tallis* and he stood in תפילה tefillah? *tefilla*, in prayer. אמר
לפניו *Amar lefanav*, and he said to God, ריבונו של עולם Ribbono
shel Olam, *Ribbono shel olam*, Master of the Universe, גלוי וידוע לפניך
שלא לכבודי עשיתי *galui veyadu'a lefanecha shelo lichvodi asiti*, I did not
do it for my honor, ולא לכבוד בית אבא עשיתי *velo lichvod
beit abba asiti*, not for the honor of my father's house, אלא
ela, לכבודך עשיתי *ela lichvodcha asiti*, I did all of this for
your honor, שיהיו מים מצויים לעולי רגלים *sheyihyu mayim metzuyim le'olei regalim*,
right? I wasn't doing a business deal, I wasn't doing anything to
get any credit, I was just trying to help out the ציבור
tzibbur. *tzibur*, I was trying to get water for those that are
coming up for the רגל *regel*. מיד נתקשרו שמים בעבים וירדו גשמים
*Miyad nitkashru shamayim be'avim veyardu geshamim*, immediately the heavens were darkened with
clouds and rain came down, עד שנתמלאו שתים עשרה מעיינות מים shteim
esre ma’ayanot mayim *ad shenitmal'u shteim esrei ma'ayanot mayim*, until the twelve
wells of water filled up back with water, והותירו *vehotiru*, and then
there was even more water, עד שיצא אדון מבית המרחץ *ad sheyatza
adon mibeit hamerchatz*. So now we go back, so the master's now
walking out of his bathhouse, sees it's raining. נקדימון Nakdimon, בן גוריון
יצא מבית המקדש *Nakdimon ben Guryon yatza mibeit haMikdash*, and Nakdimon ben
Guryon is coming out from the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beit Hamikdash*.
כשפגעו זה בזה *Keshepaga'u zeh bazeh*, when they encountered one another, אמר
לו amar lo תן לי דמי מים יותר שיש לי בידך *amar
lo ten li dmei mayim yoter sheyesh li beyadecha*. So Nakdimon said,
hey, I'm returning the wells to you, the wells filled up with
water while they were still under my, they were still rented to
me, they were still borrowed to me. So all the water that
they filled up with is now mine. So not only am I
paying you back what I owe you, but give me the leftover
water. אמר לו, amar lo so he said back to him, יודע
אני שלא הרעיש הקדוש ברוך הוא את עולמו אלא בשבילך, yodea ani
shelo hir'ish Hakadosh Baruch Hu et olamo ela bishvilcha, I know that
God, so presumably he was Jewish, right? Because he doesn't say your
God, but I know that God did not, you know, cause the
world to be, you know, tremble except for your sake, you know,
bring about all this change in nature that all of a sudden
it rained and it rained with such force. All of this was
for you. אלא עדיין יש לי פתחון פה עליך, ela adayin yesh
li pitchon peh alecha, I still have a, I still have a
טענה, taina, well, or not טענה, taina, like also like a challenge
שאוציא ממך את מעותיי she’otzi mimcha et ma’otai that I will be
able to get my money back, my money from you, those twelve
talents of silver, שכבר שקעה חמה וגשמים ברשותי, shekvar shak’ah chama ugeshamim
birshuti, the sun already set and the rain, it rained into my
wells, not into your wells. The rain came after the sun set,
so it's my rain. So ברשותי ירדו. birshuti yardu. חזר ונכנס לבית
המקדש, chazar venichnas leBeit Hamikdash, he went back into the temple, נתעטף
ועמד בתפילה, he wrapped himself in prayer, ואמר לפניו ve’amar lefanav and
said to God, ריבונו של עולם, Master of the Universe, הודע שיש
לך אהובים בעולמך, hoda sheyesh lecha ahuvim be’olamecha, know that you have
those that are beloved in your world.
מיד נתפזרו העבים, miyad nitpazeru he’avim, so what happened? The clouds separated,
scattered, וזרחה החמה, vezarcha hachama, and the sun shone forth. So he
was able to see that although it was very, very dark because
of all the rain clouds, it was still day. באותה שעה אמר
לו האדון be’otah sha’ah amar lo ha’adon and at that moment the
wealthy person said to him, אילולא נקדרה החמה היה לי פתחון פה
עליך, ilulei nikdera hachama haya li pitchon peh alecha, if the sun
had not pierced through the clouds, I would have had a challenge
against you, שאוציא ממך מעותיי, she’otzi mimcha ma’otai, that I could have
taken my money for you, but now I have to, you actually
succeed. So very powerful story or very, you know, but the question
also of like, what is the, is there like a bigger message
here? And I do think it's interesting, number one, as I said,
there is a little biblical echoes of, what do you call it?
Of like באר מים לשתות beer mayim lishtot and also it was
שתים עשרה מעיינות ma'ayanot, מים, right, is what Bnei Yisrael get when
they leave, you know, when they leave Israel, which makes it a
harder to understand, because if they were wells, it would have worked
better, but the מעיינות evokes the שתים עשרה מעיינות מים that they
find when they leave מצרים. Mitzrayim. So there are some interesting biblical
echoes. I'm sure something could be said about that. To me though,
there's also an interesting to hold this side by side to the
חוני המעגל Choni Hama'agel story. If it's been a year since there's
been rain, then it's probably פסח
time, not, not, you know, not סוכות time. And it posts to
חוני Choni where it is, you know, it's about like his, his
almost, you know, self-assuredness, if not his arrogance in his own ability
to sort of get God to do what, you know, what he
wants God to do. And he just says, yeah go ahead, take
the תנא Tanna in מסכת פסחים, Masechet Pesachim, he's so self-confident. Right,
here you have a person that's more a little, you know, sort
of the non-charismatic approach to this. Or an approach that works better
within sort of the rabbinic, you know, sort of type of establishment
approach as opposed to חוני Choni who could be a threat to
the rabbinic establishment because of his supernatural powers, as it were. So
here's a person trying to do it, you know, in a very
pragmatic way and take a type of responsibility that's presumably available to
all. You know, what does it mean to go ahead, you know,
get and make a business deal, spend some money, try to do
the practical things that are necessary? And in the end of the
story, in the end what happens? He doesn't like order God around,
he doesn't draw little circles. He also, by the way, goes into
the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. He doesn't go into his circle, right?
So the fact that חוני Choni is going into his circle at
a time when there is a בית המקדש, which seems sort of,
you know, clear from the context of that story and we know
חוני Choni lived in that time, again sort of emphasizes his, you
know, that he's operating outside of the normal establishment. Outside of the
normal centers of קדושה kedushah and of God's presence and so it's
all about, you know, his unique relationship to God. Here he goes
into the בית המקדש. He doesn't make any demands, right? You know,
he just prays, God please help us, and here God, of course,
responds in the very appropriate way. He didn't have to go through
all of the harsh rains and the light rains and, you know,
and that type of a back and forth. God is much more
immediately responsive here, right? And to the point that even, you know,
this other miracle that follows all, as that follows up, and יש
לך אהובים, yesh lecha ahuvim, you know, you have those that, you
know, you have those that love you. Meaning, again, it's much more
all-encompassing. חוני Choni is you, חוני, Choni, are בן בית. ben bayit.
Here it's like God, you know, there are people in this world
trying to, you know, trying to do the right thing, help us
out. So even while he was the one that sort of did
it, you know, his approach and his to God is much more
about not about him personally. יש לך אהובים בעולמך. yesh lecha ahuvim
be’olamecha. So I think that, I think in my mind this is
a really, you know, there’s an important contrast to the חוני המעגל
Choni Ha-Ma'agel story. All right, you had a question before?
Yeah, this in center of the law there is very extensive detailed
laws of... Water rights. This would imply that there might be some
sort of way that you can buy and sell water halachically. Right.
Is there such a thing?
Yeah, I mean sure, water is like any other object, I mean
and if it's your well, it's your water, and if it rains
in your well, then you're קונה koneh because of קניין חצר. kinyan
chatzer. So yeah, it's treated as, you know, as any other commodity.
So but yes. By the way, I did by the way misread
the word, it's not אוהבים, ohavim, it's אהובים. ahuvim. Not those that
love you, but those that you love. יש
לך אהובים. yesh lecha ahuvim. But again, even though it's אהובים, ahuvim,
it's in the plural. It's not חוני Choni who has a בן
בית, ben bayis, you חוני Choni as the one special person in
the world. There's those that you love and there's those that you
care for. So again, and by the way, here was a person
that was מוסר moseer himself for the ציבור. tzibbur, He was proactive,
right? And he was acting on behalf. חוני Choni waited for everybody
to come to him, right? They had to come for him, he
wasn't doing anything proactive. He didn't demonstrate any profound, you know, proactive
concern for the ציבור, so there's a lot of important contrasts here.
Yes, David.
I think the story is really clear, it's probably a cistern not
a well. Right. That what he's doing is he's saying I want
to lease these wells or renew a lease on them for the
time. The time comes to give them back and it hasn't rained
so the cisterns are empty. Right. And he goes and he says,
you know, God, I didn't put up a big sign that said
had my name on
it saying this is sponsored
by the water station or do it with
the יארצייט Yahrtzeit of my father, I just God this needs to
be done.
Right. So what's your question?
And then God responds.
Oh your question about the need of תפילה? tefillah? So that's a
good question, but I think that's a question that you can sort
of ask, you know, the entire מסכת. masechet. Like what's the point
of תפילה? tefillah, God doesn't know what we're doing, God doesn't know
our מעשים, ma'asim, God doesn't know our כוונות? kavanot?
You made a very strong argument about relationship, and when the relationship
needs restoration, then reflecting upon and speaking about this is not so
that's the תפילת תענית tefillat ta'anit when there is this like this
distancing, but how
do we understand the daily תפילה, tefillah, right? It sounds like God
missed the calculation. I don't think so. I don't know, when משה
Moshe says, you know, what
will מצרים Mitzrayim say and what will this and how
you know and remember the
ברית bris of
the אבות, avos, God doesn't know those things? Okay, so I know
that's the general question about the efficacy of תפילה, tefillah so I
don't know the answer to that. Okay, but anyway, but you are
right, I mean I don't understand the word מעיינות, but other than
that it evokes the biblical מעיינות, but I think it only does
make sense that it's cisterns. But yes, why does תפילה tefillah, make
a difference is a, you know, is a question that goes all
the way back. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Yes? Oh I'm sorry did you have it before? Yes, just
going back to the point of juxtaposition of the rains too early,
rains too late, rains the last minute, the בעל ba'al getting giving
it all at ערב שבת Erev Shabbos and the relationship is constantly
waxing and waning and it needs nurture and it needs attention and
we have to recognize, you know, when we get it late we
still have to make do and when it comes on time then
it's a little bit better, and the juxtaposition between those two stories.
Right, and maybe he was just making like hoping that like, you
know, by chance things would work out in his benefit and now
he actually is sort of bringing God more directly into the equation.
So even though David going
back to your point right even though he did what he did,
he didn't earlier say God please help me that this will all
work out in time that it'll rain in time, he's only now
first explicitly bringing God, you know, into it. What strikes me is
this be the impetus, in all of these stories nothing happens until
somebody cries out to God. Right. Doesn't necessarily mean that God's
going to take the initiative and provide things for us just פּאַסט
אַזוי pas azoi as my grandmother would say. Right. But when we
call out to him when we... it wasn't until he actually, you
know, humbled himself and prayed that God then responded. So I wonder
if it's what they're suggesting is there's a connection between the two
and our taking the initiative and calling out to God and then
and then God being responsive.
Right, I think so, and I think that's, you know, gets back
to what Jonathan was saying, which is I think that, yeah, I
mean look, the Rav Soloveitchik talks about this, you know, a lot
as well, which is that, you know, in terms of the, you
know, the תפילה, tefillah part of it is not just, you know,
is our own acknowledgment that or our own expression of the idea
that how we depend of our dependency on God and that it's
God that is going, you know, and that we need God's help
in all of these things and until you say that, it's not
like you're just persuading God because you're saying the words, it's actually
you're it's about the relationship as well, you're acknowledging how you know
your need for God, which you haven't yet sort of said or
acknowledged. So I think you're right that these things are You need
to be constantly in that, you know, in that communication. Did I
misphrase what you were saying? It's okay, yeah. And maybe some parallel
to the מן man in the desert when the person who was
more righteous received it more readily and the person who was less
righteous less readily in terms of this rain, sometimes more and sometimes
less. Right, right, all of these are about, yes, so I would
say that the point here of תפילה is, you know, is always
that issue about sort of acknowledging God and and sort of bringing,
you know, and and and sort of revisiting that relationship. Yes, there's
also the story, and I wonder if it exists here also in
the משנה, Mishnah, is that here it's the the patron is stepping
outside the natural order and going constant to God for rain. Right.
Right, he wasn't depending upon God for the portion till the very
end. Right, right. Similarly, a cistern is a technological innovation. Aha. It
takes man out of the natural water cycle and it's innovative. Not
dissimilar to the program of יוסף הצדיק Yosef HaTzadik in מצרים, Mitzrayim,
and also the earlier comments from the last page about what happens
when you get all your provisions from one year in advance through
השתדלות. hishtadlut. Right, right. And I actually think that maybe along the
lines of what you're saying, that the rabbis perhaps understood that a
cistern and aqueducts and all this stuff is kind of going outside
relationship, and it takes the most of those that are we're still
supposed to be bring God in the right have God as part
of that relationship. Right, not going outside but doing your השתדלות. hishtadlut.
Exactly, exactly. You know, so I think both of those are true,
and again the way I'm reading it is also that that's just
also a clear contrast to the חוני Honi story because חוני Honi
is working in supernatural ways and here, you know, this guy נקדימון
Nakdimon is actually acting in more natural ways, more this-worldly ways than
even the מסכת masechet has been, which always focus on prayer. He
says what's all this prayer, let's actually, you know, let's start trying
to address the problem. So but he is right, exactly, exactly. So
I think that that's all of those are legitimate points and it's
again an important contrast to the חוני Honi story. Okay, תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. Okay, sorry, first a wide line here. תנא: Tanna: לא
נקדימון שמו אלא בוני שמו. Lo Nakdimon shemo ela Boni shemo. His
name wasn't really נקדימון, it was בוני. Boni. ולמה נקרא שמו נקדימון?
Ve-lamah nikra shemo Nakdimon? שנקדרה חמה בעבורו, She-nikdera hachamah ba-avuro, because the
sun pierced through, so נקדימון מלשון חמה, milshon chamah, although we'll see
another use of the name in a minute. The sun pierced through
for his sake. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: שלושה נקדמה להם חמה בעבורן.
Shlosha nikdema lahem hachamah ba-avuran. So now it's not נקדרה, nikdera, קודרת
kodert to pierce through, but נקדמה, nikdema, preceded for their sake. The
sun sort of did not stayed back for their sake, did not
set in its right time: משה, יהושע ונקדימון בן גוריון. Moshe, Yehoshua
ve-Nakdimon ben Goryon. בשלמא נקדימון בן גוריון גמרא, Beshalma Nakdimon ben Goryon
gemara, that's a tradition, that's how we know it. Now all of
a sudden the story has changed. Not just was it rain and
that you know and it was okay God intervened but in a
natural way and the sun shone through the clouds, but actually the
sun should have set, and that's why it really shouldn't have been
they being paid back the debt. And God kept the sun, held
the sun back from setting so that he would be able to
pay back his debt. So now we actually have him as doing
something as equally or God doing something as equally miraculous for him
as God did for יהושע Yehoshua and we'll soon see משה. Moshe.
Can we understand it the opposite too with the same meaning? In
other words, it rained on his behalf, right? Did it not rain
for him? Right, so קדר kedar means to darken. Oh. So the
sky darkened. Yeah but that wasn't the verb used before, right? It
says, no you're right, it says... but wait a minute, wait a
minute, wait a minute, so the אדון said אילו לא נקדרה חמה
היה לי פתחון פה. Ilu lo nikdera hachamah hayah li pitchon peh.
So but I see your point, maybe there's a double play. Okay,
that could be. But here clearly it's about the sun not setting.
יהושע נמי קרא כתיב, Yehoshua nami kra ketiv, by יהושע Yehoshua it's
a verse: וידום השמש וירח עמד. Va-yidom ha-shemesh ve-yarei'ach amad. אלא משה
מנלן? Ela Moshe minalan? So משה Moshe is the only one we
don't know had this miracle occur to him. So where do we
know this from? So רבי אליעזר אשכחיה אחל אחל. Rabbi Eliezer ashkechei
Akhel Akhel. כתיב הכא אחל תת פחדך, Ketiv hacha Akhel tait pachtecha,
God says to משה, Moshe, I will begin to give your fear
תחת כל השמים, tachat kol ha-shamayim, וכתיב התם ve-chetiv hatam by יהושע,
Yehoshua, אחל גדלך, Akhel gadlecha, I will begin to raise you up.
So with the same tremendous גדולה, gedulah, you know, that occurred to
יהושע Yehoshua occurred to משה. Moshe. רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר אתיא
תת תת. Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar atya tait tait. כתיב הכא
אחל תת פחדך Ketiv hacha Akhel tait pachtecha by משה, Moshe, I'll
begin to place your fear, the fear of you, וכתיב התם ביום
תת ה' את האמורי, ve-chetiv hatam be-yom tait Hashem et ha-Emori, so
by יהושע. Yehoshua. So גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. רבי יוחנן אמר מגופיה
דקרא, Rabbi Yochanan amar mi-gufeh d'kra, it's implicit in the verse: אשר
ישמעון את שמעך ורגזו וחלו מפניך, Asher yishme'un et shimacha ve-ragzu ve-chalu
mipanecha, God says to משה, Moshe, they'll hear of your reputation and
tremble and shake from before you. must be the same miracle occurred.
I don't know exactly how you get that from the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*, something maybe happened, but exactly that miracle is not clear. But
again here now you do have this amazing thing, right? Because you
have this person who's basically what he did was operated in the
most this-worldly way,
right, this נקדימון *Nakdimon*, and he's getting the same miracles that משה
*Moshe* and יהושע *Yehoshua* and the same changing of nature, you know,
the most dramatic change of natural law, it's not just that it
rains, that משה *Moshe* and יהושע *Yehoshua* got. So it's really I
think a powerful message about not that people will have these miracles
done for them, but about, you know, the this-worldly type of leadership
that he embraced and the power of that. Okay, וכן עיר שלא
ירדו עליה גשמים *vechen ir shelo yardu aleha geshamim*. Now back to
the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, a city that does not have rain, if
it rained in some city, you know, in one city and not
in another city, and the whole issue was that the city that
didn't have rain, you know, would fast and the other city would
not fast, but then other types of things with the surrounding cities
or villages would participate in a lesser way. And it quotes a
פסוק *pasuk* and the פסוק *pasuk* is
על עיר אחת אמטיר ועל עיר אחת לא אמטיר *al ir achat
amtir ve'al ir achat lo amtir*. I'll bring rain on one city,
not on the other. So אמר רב Rav, יהודה אמר רב ושתיהן
לקללה *amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav ushteihen liklala*.
You would think that the city that gets rain is a ברכה
*bracha* and the city that doesn't get rain is a קללה *klala*.
It's possible they'll both be a curse. Now this isn't exactly spelled
out, but at least anyway the way some of the commentators say,
it means that if it means
that those that don't have will then all go to buy their
grain from the other city, it's not exactly clear how that's a
curse, that's good for business. So some say it means that no,
the city that did have could have that
it could have too much rain.
So a shortage. What? A bit of a shortage. Okay, it creates
if the demand outstrips the supply, yeah. More of a shortage. Ah,
that's a good point. Good, ah, okay. You don't know how it
could be good and bad, how it could be bad for those
that have that got the rain? Well, I mean, it would be
more of a shortage if both of them didn't have rain. So
anyway, רש"י *Rashi* says that it means that it's just
that it would be too much rain.
Sometimes too much can also be a קללה *klala*, even though you
don't pray for רוב גשמים *rov geshamim*. Anyway, it's not so clear.
Now we're going to go have a number of statements אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב *amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav* doing the reverse, taking
verses that look like a curse and saying that they're really a
blessing.
Oh, exactly this verse. Exactly.
היתה ירושלים לנדה ביניהם *haysa Yerushalayim lenida beineihem*.
Excellent point, mentioning that, we're going to get to בלעם Bilam. *Bilam*
in a minute anyway. היתה ירושלים לנדה ביניהם *haysa Yerushalayim lenida beineihem*.
So Jerusalem was for a נדה *nida*, like a menstruant woman among
them, obviously showing the way that a נדה *nida* in, you know,
in ancient society would have been treated as an outcast, a larger
discussion. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב לברכה *amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
levracha*. That's a blessing. כנדה *kenida*. מה נדה יש לה היתר *ma
nida yesh la heter*. The same way a woman who's a נדה
*nida* eventually becomes permissible to her husband, Jerusalem will be once again
in its former state. נדה *nida* is not a permanent state. היתה
כאלמנה *haysa k'almana*. She was like a widow. אמר רב יהודה לברכה
*amar Rav Yehuda levracha*. That's a blessing in that. כאלמנה *k'almana*. Like
a widow. ולא אלמנה ממש *velo almana mamash*. Not a real widow,
אלא כאישה שהלך בעלה למדינת הים ודעתו לחזור עליה *ela k'isha shehalach
ba'ala lemedinas hayam veda'aso lachzor aleha*. A woman whose husband has gone
overseas, maybe she hasn't seen him for years, but eventually he'll be
coming back. וגם אני נתתי אתכם נבזים ושפלים *vegam ani nasati eschem
nivzim ushfalim*. I have placed you that, you know, degraded and lowly.
אמר רב יהודה לברכה *amar Rav Yehuda levracha*. There's a blessing in
that. דלא מוקמי מינן לא ראשי נהרי ולא גזירפטי *d'la mokmi minan
la rashei naharei velo gezirpati*, that they don't because the non-Jews think
that we're so lowly and despicable, they don't make us tax collectors
and they don't make us, you know, soldiers or some say it
means like officers, like police officers that would, you know, beat people.
We don't get these jobs which are jobs of status but also
jobs that are morally, you know, deeply problematic. I mean, you know,
because the Jews were so despised that they weren't allowed to own
land is how they got to be moneylenders and how they got
to be, right, was a major source of serious antagonism but also
of wealth, you know.
So sometimes that became, sometimes there's a hidden blessing in some of
that pushing them to those other professions. והכה השם את ישראל Yisrael
כאשר ינוד הקנה במים *vehika Hashem es Yisrael ka'asher yanud hakane bamayim*.
God will smite the Jewish people
the same way the reed will sway in water. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב לברכה *amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav levracha*. There's a blessing
in that. דאמר רבי Rebbe שמואל Shmuel בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן *de-amar Rebbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rebbi Yonasan*.
מאי דכתיב De-chsiv, *mai dechesiv*. What does it mean? נאמנים פצעי אוהב
*ne'emanim pitz'ei ohev*. Trustworthy are the smites of one who loves you.
ונעתרות נשיקות שונא *vena'ataros nishikos soneh*. And burdensome, I don't know exactly
how to translate that word, but burdensome are the kisses of one
who hates you. So you'd rather get hit by your friend than
kissed by your enemy. So what does that mean? טובה קללה שקילל
*tova klala shekilel*. אחיה השילוני, Achiyah Hashiloni. so this פסוק about the
reed swaying in water was from the נביא navi אחיה השילוני. Achiyah
Hashiloni So better is that is that curse that he cursed at
ישראל Yisrael, יותר מברכה שבירכן בלעם הרשע. yoter mibracha sheberchan Bilam Harasha.
There you go. So not so the blessing it's better than the
blessing of בלעם. Bilam אחיה השילוני cursed them ודימהן vedimehan that they
would be like a reed. אמר להם לישראל, amar lahem leYisrael, ויתשם
את ישראל כאשר ינוד הקנה. vitashem et Yisrael kaasher yanud hakanah. מה
קנה זה עומד במקום מים ma kaneh zeh omed bemakom mayim so
let's think about it. The reed can stand in a place of
water, stands, number one, it grows in a place of water, right?
It's there in the middle of the water. וגיזו מחליף vegizo machalif
and it constantly is like replenishing its stalk. ושרשיו מרובים vesharshav merubim
and it has very many and deep roots. ואפילו כל רוחות שבעולם
באות ונושבות בו אין מזיזות אותו ממקומו, vaafilu kol ruchot shebaolam baot
venoshvot bo ein miziizot oto mimakomo, no matter how strong the winds
are, they don't move it from its place, right? It's very flexible
and its roots are deep. אלא הולך ובא עמהן, ella holech uba
imahen, it sways with the wind, ודממו הרוחות עמד הקנה במקומו, vadamemu
haruchot amad hakanah bimakomo, and when the wind stop, אמר הקנה במקומו,
amad hakanah bimakomo, it's still where it always was. So the ability
to sort of, on the one hand, be deeply rooted and on
the other hand be able to deal with all of the terrible
things that pass over and that, you know, there's a blessing in
that. ואילו בלעם הרשע בירכן בארז, veilu Bilam Harasha berchan beerez, the
wicked בלעם Bilaam blessed them with a cedar, שנאמר, shenemar, the verse
says, כארזים עלי מים, kaarasim alei mayim, like cedars by the water.
They take out that part of עלי מים alei mayim as a
minute, you'll see why. מה ארז זה אינו עומד במקום מים ma
erez zeh eino omed bemakom mayim because cedars normally, although the verse
says עלי מים, alei mayim, but nevertheless, cedars normally do not stand
in a place where there's a plentiful water. ואין גיזו מחליף vein
gizo machalif and its trunk does not replenish ואין שרשיו מרובים vein
sharshav merubim and it does not have very many deep roots. ואפילו
כל רוחות שבעולם נושבות בו אין מזיזות אותו ממקומו, afilu kol ruchot
shebaolam noshvot bo ein miziizot oto mimakomo, while it's true that normal
winds cannot move it from its place, כיון שנשבה רוח דרומית עקרתהו
והפכתהו על פניו, keivan shenashvah ruach dromit okartahu vehofchatohu al panav, what's
a strong southern wind comes, that can uproot it from its place.
ולא עוד, velo od, so therefore, the idea that you're a lowly
reed, there's a blessing in that. It means that you're not, you
know, that you're able to sway with the winds, you're and you
stay rooted and you'll always be, you know, replenished. ולא עוד אלא
שזכה קנה ליטול ממנו קולמוס לכתוב בו ספר תורה נביאים וכתובים. velo
od ella shezachah kaneh litol mimenu kulmos lichtov bo sefer torah neviim
uktuvim. And this lowly reed also, not only, you know, is able
to survive but also serves very, because it's so lowly, it gets
used in very profound religious purposes. Through it you write the תורה
נביאים וכתובים. Torah Neviim uktuvim. So ישראל, you know, they're of a
lowly status in a worldly sense, but they're a vehicle of קדושה.
kedushah. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught, לעולם יהא אדם רך
כקנה ואל יהא קשה כארז.
leolam yehei adam rach kakaneh veall yehei
kasheh keerez.
So using the same imagery we just used, a person should always
be as soft, as flexible, as bending as
a reed and
not as hard, not as unbending as a cedar. מעשה שבא רבי
אליעזר, maaseh sheba Rabbi Eliezer, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar, some have the גרסא girsa of רבי אליעזר
בן רבי שמעון, Rabbi Eliezer ben Rabbi Shimon,
ממגדל גדור, mimigdal gedor, very famous story. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
was coming from
מגדל גדור, Migdal Gedor, a place. Now it's interesting just to note
what those two words mean, right? מגדל Migdal is a castle, a
tower, and גדור Gedor is like a fenced-in castle. So he was
coming from his academy, from his castle in the sky. Okay, he
was coming from having learned תורה Torah in this very, you know,
hermetically sealed environment. ממגדל גדור, mimigdal gedor, מבית רבו, mibeit rabo, from
his master's house.
והיה רכוב על חמור ומטייל על
שפת הנהר.
vehaya rachuv al chamor umitayal al
sefat hanahar.
He was, he was riding, I guess רכוב rachuv or רוכב, rochev,
רכוב על חמור, rachuv al chamor, he was riding on the donkey
and he was, you know, slowly going by, you know, traveling, not
traveling, what's the word for מטייל? mitayal? Yeah, anyway, he wasn't in
any rush, he was just, you know, strolling, strolling by. I don't
know if you can stroll on a donkey. In the shade? Oh,
taking the shade instead of something in the sun? Maybe. Okay, anyway,
he was strolling on his donkey there by the riverside. ושמח שמחה
גדולה vesamach simchah gedolah and he was feeling very self-satisfied, he was
feeling very happy with himself. וישד דעתו גסה עליו, vayashet daato gasah
alav, he was feeling, you know, very proud, very how great he
was, he had learned all this תורה, Torah, מפני שלמד תורה הרבה,
mipnei shelamad torah harbeh, because he learned a lot of תורה. Torah.
Okay, so that's the setup. I do want to say something about
riding on the donkey and maybe I'm reading a little bit into
it, but who else is riding on a donkey? משיח, Mashiach, right?
So maybe he had a little bit of a messianic complex. He
was thinking he was God's gift. He was thinking, oh my God,
look how wonderful I am. That's and here he is. Okay. What
did you say? He had a little Jesus? Right, okay, sorry, it's
that other religion. ונזדמן לו אדם אחד, venizman lo adam echad, a
certain man came upon him. According to some versions, this is אליהו
הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi who's coming to teach him a lesson. Okay, it's
not explicit in this story. שהיה מכוער ביותר shehaya mecho'ar beyoter and
he was very ugly, he was very you know unseemly. אמר לו
amar lo and he he this man treated this rabbi with respect.
שלום עליך רבי, Shalom Alecha Rebbe, peace to you my master. שלא
החזיר לו, shelo hechzir lo, he did not respond to him. He
didn't say you know שלום עליך. Shalom Alecha. He was so beneath
his you know the worst he was so you know he wasn't
even worthy of a response. אמר לו and but now he did
say to him like he didn't respond to him to respond to
him would have made him somehow socially equal so he refused to
respond but now he has something to say to him okay to
say down to him. אמר לו and he said to him ריקא,
reika, you empty person כמה מכוער אותו האיש, kama mecho'ar oto ha'ish,
how disgusting you are, how ugly you are. שמא כל בני עירך
מכוערים כמותך, shema kol benei ircha mecho'arim kemotecha, like maybe all the
people of your city are as disgusting as you are. אמר לו
he said back to him איני יודע, eini yode'a, I don't know
how you know my other people in my city. אלא, but if
you've got a problem לך ואמור לאומן שעשאני, lech ve'emor la'uman she'asani,
go back and tell the craftsman who made me כמה מכוער כלי
זה שעשית, kama mecho'ar kli zeh she'asita, how disgusting is this vessel
that you have made.
So I do want to say something else about this which is
also that right presumably the message here is is that the real
person who was ugly right was
the rabbi right the sort of the ugliness inside as opposed to
the ugliness on the outside but it's interesting that he calls him
ריקא, reika, empty person because the ריק reik means what's on your
inside right and that's sort of part of the whole problem here
is that he's calling him ריקא reika but he's looking at the
outside and he's calling him ריקא, reika, he's not he's not really
caring or seeing what's inside. The other thing is when he responded
איני יודע eini yode'a right so presumably most people will know what
the people of their city look like right but he actually is
sort of saying like taking a humble response you know I don't
know they you know I don't think I know everything okay but
here's so here's one thing I do know this isn't how you
talk to people and this isn't a proper way of religious acting
but as opposed to you you think you know everything you know
you came back from ישיבה yeshiva sometimes you have this anyway you
know kids come back from Israel all of a sudden like they
know everything okay you think you know everything you know what's inside
of me you know how to assess me you know how to
value me you know. And the rabbi I knew everything when I
was 19 exactly so you know so he's also sort of modeling
a response of איני יודע eini yode'a okay so I don't know
but here's the one thing I do know. Okay so וכיון שידע
בעצמו שחטא, vecheivan sheyada be'atzmo shechata, as soon as he realized that
he had sinned ירד מן החמור, yarad min hachamor, he came down
off the donkey so he came off of his high elevated status
coming down to earth right ונשתטח לפניו venishtate'ach lefanav and prostrated himself
in front of him ואמר לו ve'amar lo נעניתי לך na'aniti lecha
I have now you know it's an interesting verb because again we
have the word לא נענו lo na'anu they were not responded but
does this also mean that I am like subjugated to you you
know or I am hearing you and I am responding how do
they translate נעניתי לך na'aniti lecha there in the English? I was
crushed and nish- something nish- I have spoken out of turn to
you נעניתי לך na'aniti lecha I have spoken out of turn? I
don't get how do they translate it in the in Steinzaltz? I
have sinned. What? I have sinned against you. And what do they
say before the word I have sinned? Now you finding it? Okay
anyway obviously it means something along those lines. What? It is parallel
to בלעם when he gets off his donkey and he says to
the and he has a he has the donkey no but when
he you know he sees the angel right he gets he realized
what's in front of him and he gets down on the oh
that's a nice point the getting off of the donkey and the
and the sort of realizing what you have in scene and what
you've done wrong it's a nice point. Okay so anyway somehow I
sinned before you oh no you're right Shelley it's just נעניתי na'aniti
translating נעניתי na'aniti is and surely that's what that means in context
although I don't exactly get what the you know what the source
what the root of that verb is anyway I have sinned to
you or I've spoken out of turn from the word like עונה
ona I guess but anyway I've spoken out of turn מחול לי,
mechol li, forgive me. אמר לו and he said to him איני
מוחל לך, eini mochel lecha, I will not forgive you עד שתלך
לאומן שעשאני ad shetelech la'uman she'asani until you go back to the
craftsman that made me ואמור לו ve'emor lo כמה מכוער כלי זה
שעשית, kama mecho'ar kli zeh she'asita, how disgusting is this vessel that
you have made. Now probably what he is saying is is that
you have not really fully owned how bad it what it is
that you have done you don't just get a quick easy forgiveness
right there's no תשובה teshuvah here I mean it's just oh my
God I just did something wrong you know please forgive me where
is any sense of doing תשובה teshuvah where is any sense of
owning you know the what as how offensive this was not just
to to me but to God. היה מטייל אחריו עד שהגיע לעירו
haya metayel acharav ad shehigia le'iro so he was following after him
until until he came to his city meaning presumably it means the
city the city the the. Rabbi city as we will see. So
the Rabbi was following after him until they came to the Rabbi's
city. יצאו בני עירו לקראתו. Yatzu bnei iro likrato. The people of
his city came out to greet him. ויאמרו לו שלום עליך רבי
רבי מורי מורי, Vayomru lo shalom alecha Rebbe Rebbe mori mori, peace
be to you, Rebbe Rebbe, our master, our master. So אמר להם,
Amar lahem, so the, this person, this man who was insulted, said
to them, למי אתם קוראים רבי רבי? Lemi atem korim Rebbe Rebbe?
Who is this person you say Rebbe Rebbe? אמרו לו, Amru lo,
לזה שמטייל אחריך, Laze shemetayel acharecha, the person traveling behind you. Now
by the way, this also gives us a little insight why he
did not, when he was on his donkey, did not respond to
him. Right? Can you see now why he wouldn't respond to him
when he was greeted? What did the guy say to him? He
said, שלום עליך רבי. Shalom alecha Rebbe. What's, how's this guy used
to being greeted? שלום עליך רבי רבי מורי מורי. Shalom alecha Rebbe
Rebbe mori mori. This guy is such a disgusting looking guy and
he doesn't even know how to address me with all the honor
that I deserve, right? So we get a little bit more of
an insight of why he, you know, why he refused to, you
know, and he saw that as a bad reflection on the person.
Oh my God, he only calls me Rebbe, right? And obviously what
it really is reflecting on is himself. Okay. אמר, so it's who
are you calling this person Rebbe Rebbe? The guy behind you? אמר
להם, Amar lahem, he said to them, אם זה רבי, Im ze
Rebbe, if this is a teacher, אל ירבו כמותו בישראל. Al yirbu
kamoso b'Yisrael. Again a play on רבי and ירבו, yirbu, right? So
if this is a teacher, there should not be many of him
in Israel. אמרו לו מפני מה? Amru lo mipnei ma? Why? Right?
They said to him, why? אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said back
to them, כך וכך עשה לי. Kach v'kach asa li. Look what
he did to me. He said all, you know, he called me
אדם מכוער, Adam mechuar, how he treated me. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
they said to him, אף על פי כן מחול לו. Af al
pi chen mechol lo. Nevertheless, we're not coming to make any excuse,
you should nevertheless forgive him, שאדם גדול בתורה הוא. She'adam gadol baTorah
hu. He is a great person in Torah. And I think even
there the idea is, right, he is גדול, Gadol, right? And he
said, you know, there's still this sense of, meaning it could just
be read as the פשט, pshat, he's a big תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham and nevertheless, but I could also think again that it's getting
to the heart of the problem, right, that he has all of
his status and his sense of how great he is is tied
in, you know, is due to his Torah. Not so, so in
their very defense of him, it's also reflecting, you know, he didn't
say he's a צדיק, tzaddik, he's good במעשים טובים. b'ma'asim tovim. It's
all about his Torah and how גדול Gadol he is בתורה. baTorah.
הוא. Hu. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to them, בשבילכם הריני
מוחל לו. Bishvilchem hareni mochel lo. For you, not for him. He
hasn't done, he hasn't done the right תשובה teshuvah he needs. He's
still a problem. For you, I'll forgive him. ובלבד שלא יהא רגיל
לעשות כן, Uvilvad shelo yehei ragil la'asos ken, as long as he
doesn't accustom himself to doing this. Now that is a very bizarre
response. It should say ובלבד שלא יעשה כן, ubilvad shelo ya'aseh ken,
right, he shouldn't do this at all in the future. What's שלא
יהא רגיל לעשות כן? shelo yehei ragil la'asos ken? He shouldn't accustom
himself to doing it. So you could say he was being just
very realistic. Somebody like this is not going to have a real
personality change, right? So maybe the best you can do is try
to control this attitude and not completely eradicate it. The מהרש"א says
it means don't practice in a way, don't be מתרגל mitragel yourself,
don't do the types of actions that encourage this type of an
attitude. So maybe if you're going to learn, don't like lock yourself
off from real people and go riding around on a donkey rather
than being down on the earth and you know, and interacting with
the, you know, with normal people, you know. So or other types
of things that make you feel how, you know, how lofty you
are because of the Torah. Don't be מתרגל mitragel yourself, you know,
don't put yourself, don't, don't do types of practices that encourage this
arrogant way of looking at the world. מיד נכנס רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון. Miyad nichnas Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon. So immediately the, this Rabbi,
Rabbi Elazar Rabbi Shimon went in, ודרש, v'darash, presumably to the synagogue,
and expounded, לעולם יהא אדם רך כקנה ואל יהא קשה כארז. Le'olam
yehei adam rach kakaneh v'al yehei kasheh ka'erez. A person should always
be as soft, as pliable as a reed and not as harsh
as a cedar. ולפיכך זכה קנה ליטול ממנו קולמוס לכתוב בו ספר
תורה תפילין ומזוזות. Ulfichach zacha kaneh litol mimenu kulmus lichtov bo sefer
torah tefillin umezuzos. Therefore the reed had a, for, taken a quill
to write the Sefer Torah, Tefillin and Mezuzos. Now, how is that
related? Who is he talking to? The bad guy is the ugly
man in this story. So, so if he's saying, look this guy
didn't forgive me! I said please forgive me, I traveled after him
and he was being קשה כארז. kasheh ka'erez. Right, that would really
show somebody who had not at all learned his lesson. Now I
think that that is a subtext. I think that and the, at
the surface level, what we're supposed to have him understand is A
that I need to, I need to stop being a haughty as
an ארז erez and I need to learn a little bit of
humility. And B, notice also that the אדם מכוער adam mechuar referred
to himself as כלי זה, kli ze, this vessel. A vessel, so
he is an ugly vessel, but he is a vessel created by
God and God created vessel God he's some, you know, doesn't mean
that he's just created by God. You use a vessel. Right? So
here you have something that looks maybe ugly but used. Ultimately it
can be the most profound and sublime vessel. And that's what the
קנה Kaneh is, right? It's lowly, it's maybe not ugly, but it's
lowly, and it becomes the vessel for writing תפילין Tfillin and מזוזות.
Mezuzot. So maybe there is the acknowledgment, I think there's three possible
meanings of this דרשה. Derasha. Number one is, I shouldn't have been
as haughty. The other thing, which is the parallel, is even a
lowly ugly vessel can be a tremendous vessel of קדושה. Kedusha. But
I agree with Dov's point that I also think that he might
feel be critiquing this man even at the very end, and so
might be saying, and you, you should have been more responsive than
you actually were. And he was pliant, because his original plan was
not to forgive, and then he forgave at the end, so there
was some, that's true, he was pliant at that stage. Not because
of the rabbi, but because of the people, but that's right, yeah.
He was more pliant. Right. Regarding an ארז Erez being negative, what
about צדיק כתמר יפרח? Tzadik Katamar Yifrach? Yeah, that's a problem. Obviously
there are positive images with trees and so on, but we're using
this to make this point. Okay, yes. Whichever of the two it
may be, although I'd be more inclined to the first one, what
gets lost in it is how fundamentally problematic, it seems to me,
is the response of the people to him. And they told him,
you forgive him anyway because he's a תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. Because
they know, that's the problem. The problem is that he gets a
pass, that's exactly, exactly, exactly, you know, that's the whole problem is
that people give him a pass for this behavior because he's a
תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and in a way that serves as a
terrible model for what, right, I think. It seems to be sanctioned.
Right. I think that that's a very good point. You're right. I
don't have an answer to that. You're absolutely right. Yeah. All right.
ובכן, U-v'chen, let's start to read one, begin one more section. שיש
בו דבר או מפולת. Sheyesh Bo Dever O Mapolet. Now we get
to the types of things that you fast in nearby towns, or
you pray in nearby towns, it's not the same severity because they're
somehow connected. And the two things that are mentioned in the משנה
Mishna, are דבר, Dever, this pestilence, oh no, I'm sorry, we're not
yet to the nearby town thing, are we? Oh yes, we are.
Okay. So it's this pestilence and the falling buildings. So we will
see, as some of you already sort of figured out in the
משנה, that the falling buildings are not that the buildings aren't constructed
well, but are as that there's earthquakes or that there's very terrible
winds and things that could affect the neighboring towns as well. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught: מפולת שאמרו בריאות ולא רעועות, Mapolet
She'amru Beriot V'lo Re'uot, it's only if healthy buildings, strong buildings fall
down, not if weak buildings fall down. That doesn't prove anything, that's
just a weak building. שאינן ראויות ליפול ולא הראויות ליפול, She'einan Re'uyot
Lipol V'lo Hare'uyot Lipol, buildings that were not normally fit to fall
down and that were constructed in ways that they should have stood
for a very long time, but we're not talking ones that were
about to fall, that were not that, okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says, aren't those the same things? היינו בריאות היינו שאינן ראויות. Heinu
Beriot Heinu She'einan Re'uyot. Why do you need two definitions? Healthy buildings
or buildings that are not fit to fall down? שאינן ראויות ליפול.
She'einan Re'uyot Lipol. והיינו רעועות היינו ראויות ליפול, V'heinu Re'uot Heinu Re'uyot
Lipol, shaky buildings, it's the same way of saying buildings that are
fit to fall down. So what's the purpose of saying these two
descriptors? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא דנפיש מחמת גובהיה. Lo
Tzericha Denafish Machamat Govhei. You can have something that is structurally sound
or made of sound materials, it's not rotting away, but it is
way too tall for its so that it's ראויה ליפול Re'uya Lipol
even though it's לא רעועה, Lo Re'ua, right? So it's not dilapidated,
it's not a crumbling building, it's made of good strong new building
materials, but the way it's constructed is it still could fall down.
אינמי דקיימא אגודא דנהרא, Inami Dekayma Aguda Denahra, or let's say it's
built right at the edge of a river. It could be very
strong materials, but if the river overflows or eats away at the
ground underneath, it could collapse. So there's other reasons it could be
fit to fall in addition to it being dilapidated and crumbling. כי
ההיא שיתא רעועה, Ki Hahi Shita Re'ua, there was a trembling wall,
a wall that was in bad shape, דהוה בנהרדעא, Dehava Bi'nehardea, that
was in Nehardea, ולא חלפו רב ושמואל תותיה, V'lo Chalfu Rav U'shmuel
Tutei, that Rav and Shmuel would not walk under it, אף על
גב דקיימא אפרתסר שנין, Af Al Gav Dekayma Afartaser Shnin, even though
that it was there for thirteen years, they still said, it's constructed
in a way that it could fall anytime, there's always going to
be that one moment in time when it actually falls. And they
did not take the fact that it had survived for thirteen years
to say that we don't have to worry about it. Now presumably
again, רעועה Re'ua here is not, it's funny because it's trying to
bring a proof for something that could be well-constructed and still maybe
about to fall. That was something that is not רעועה. Re'ua. Here
the wall is being defined as רעועה. Re'ua. But nevertheless, the message
seems to be that even if something looks like it's been standing
a long time and doesn't look dilapidated, it might be constructed in
a way that it could fall in any moment. יומא חד איקלא
רב אדא בר אהבה להתם. Yoma chad ikla Rav Adda bar Ahava
le-hasam. One day רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava visited
that place. אמר ליה שמואל לרב Amar leh Shmuel le-Rav and then
they were taking a walk with him and they came to this
wall, so שמואל said to רב, ניסי מנכפיס, neisei mankafis, let's go
walk around the wall like we always do. אמר ליה, Amar leh,
לא צריך השתא. lo tzarich hashta. No, today we don't have to
walk around the wall. Why? דאיכא רב אדא בר אהבה בהדן. De-ika
Rav Adda bar Ahava behadan. רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar
Ahava is with us and he is such a, you know, a
meritorious, you know, he's such a צדיק, tzaddik, a virtuous man, that
דנפיש זכותיה, de-nafish zechusei, that his merits are enormous, ולא מסתפינא, ve-lo
mistafina, I'm not afraid that the wall will fall down, his merits
will protect us. So רב הונא Rav Huna הוה ליה ההוא חמרא.
hava leh hahu chamra. רב הונא Rav Huna had some wine בההוא
בי סריא be-hahu bei sarya in a house that was dilapidated ובעי
לפנויה u-ba'ei le-fanuyei and he was afraid to go into the cellar
to get the wine, the whole house could collapse on him at
any moment ובעי לפנויה u-ba'ei le-fanuyei and he wanted to get his
wine out of there. So what did he do? איילי לרב אדא
בר אהבה להתם, Aylei le-Rav Adda bar Ahava le-hasam, he took רב
אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava there ומשכיה בשמעתא u-mashchei be-shma'ata
and he got in a conversation with רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav
Adda bar Ahava, he started talking to him in Torah. They started
on a walk, he said, "Oh look, here's this house, I've got
some wine," and they continued walking into the house and talking in
Torah עד דפניה ad de-panya until he got his wine out of
the house, and he was all along keeping רב אדא בר אהבה
Rav Adda bar Ahava there talking in Torah. בתר דנפיק Basar de-nafik
and then the moment they left the house נפל ביתא, nafal beisa,
the house fell down. So רגש רב אדא בר אהבה, Regash Rav
Adda bar Ahava, so רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava
had a sense of how he was being used. It's funny, until
that point he didn't have a sense. He is so caught up
in his Torah as we're going to see. רב אדא בר אהבה
Rav Adda bar Ahava is like completely immersed in Torah that he
wasn't even aware about which house are we in, what's going on
here, he's just talking in Torah. When the house actually collapsed, he
got a sense about something was up. Okay, so ארגש, irgesh, he
had a sense that something was up. איקפד, itped, he got a
little bit upset. סבר לה, Savar lah, he said, כי הא דאמר
רב ינאי, ki ha de-amar Rav Yannai, לעולם אל יעמוד אדם במקום
סכנה ויאמר עושין לי נס שמא אין עושין לו נס. le-olam al
ya'amod adam bi-mekom sakana ve-yomar osin li nes shema ein osin lo
nes. He says a person should never go in a place of
danger and say a miracle will be done because maybe even somebody
who is deserving, the miracle won't be done ואם תמצא לומר עושין
לו נס ve-im timtza lomar osin lo nes and if the miracle
is done מנכין לו מזכויותיו, menakin lo mi-zechuyosav, it's counted against your
merits. אמר רב חנן מאי קרא, Amar Rav Chanan mai kra, where
do we see it? דכתיב, the verse says קטנתי מכל החסדים ומכל
האמת. katonti mi-kol ha-chasadim u-mi-kol ha-emes. So it literally means I'm undeserving
of God's kindness, but it basically, but here it means saying I
have been made small because of God's kindness, now that has shrunk
my account of merits. So, you know, my wife has this mentality
or whatever, she was brought up with this mentality. So like whenever
like, you know, we get some like thing like, like we find
a parking space exactly where we need it in Manhattan or something
like that, she says, "Using up some עולם הבא olam ha-ba right
there." So anyway, but okay, but here you have this person who's
protecting them with his tremendous merits. Again, interesting to think how this
might be a different image from the חוני המעגל image. Here he's
completely even unaware of his powers and what's doing and other people
are sort of, you know, using him in this way and here
it's all about Torah as we will see. So we will continue
with this tomorrow. We'll let's just end by saying a קל מלא
Kel Malei for the for the.